Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is כ"ב, Chaf-Bet, 22.
We start on כ"ב Chaf-Bet and we are dealing with the actual
experience of or the process of התרת נדרים, Hataras Nedarim, releasing people
from vows, established that there are two things: חרטה, charata, which is
just 'I wish I had never done it', that's about the whole
thing; and then there's פתח, pesach, which is 'had I been thinking
of this, then I never would have done it in the first
place', so there's an element of error at the time. In hindsight
you could identify that, you know, like you can say like, 'at
the time, had I been fully thinking through the issues, I wouldn't
have done it', and that's more what the גמרא Gemorah says is
more similar to the ארבעה נדרים Arba Nedarim of our משנה, Mishna,
where in the ארבעה נדרים Arba Nedarim of our משנה Mishna you
never, it's clear you were not did not mean it at the
time. Here you're sort of saying, 'had I been fully thinking, I
wouldn't have meant it', and that's sort of that's more similar to
that. And so there's the question, obviously פתח pesach is the better
way to go, it makes it more obvious, you know, that why
it's not binding, it shows more of the weight as אבו דהו
Avu de-hu said about the whole, you know, נדר neder itself and
the power of that. But so that's the question: when you somebody
comes for התרת נדרים, Hataras Nedarim, do you, you know, must you
start with פתח pesach or can you even go straight to the
just simple חרטה? charata? So that's the question: whether פותחין בחרטה potchin
b'charata or not. And again to clarify, חרטה charata is not like
'I'm happy I did it until now, but now I, you know,
from now here on in I don't want to be bound by
it', because then there would never be a process, it's always the
case of somebody who wants to get out of a vow. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemorah is going through a series of cases, some
rabbis who allowed vows based on חרטה charata and some who did
it based on פתח. pesach. And now we pick up with the
following,
three lines from the top of כ"ב עמוד א: Chaf-Bet Amud Aleph:
בר ברתה דרבי ינאי, Bar Barteh d'Rabbi Yannai, the son of the
daughter of רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, his grandson, סבא, Sabba, רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai the elder or רבה, Rabba, אתא לקמיה דרבי ינאי, ata
lekamei d'Rabbi Yannai, came to his grandfather, came to רבי ינאי סבא.
Rabbi Yannai Sabba. אמר ליה, Amar leh, and said to him, and
presumably he had a vow that he wanted to get out of,
and so רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai said to him: אילו הוה ידעת
דפתחין פנקסך ומשמשמין בעובדך, Ilu hava yadata d'paskin pinkaska umishamshimin b'uvdach,
if you had known that up in heaven when you take a
vow they're going to open up your ledger and check out your
deeds, that your act of taking a vow makes them up in
heaven then them take a much closer look at you. Like we
all think that we're honest when we fill out our taxes, but
who really wants to have a tax audit, right? So therefore you
take a vow, you're going to undergo a tax audit, okay. So,
had you known that, that that's what that would happen up in
heaven, מי נדרת, mi nadarta, would you have taken a vow? אמר
ליה לא, Amar leh lo, no. ושרי ליה, Veshari leh, and he
permitted him. אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, מאי קרא, mai kra,
where's the verse that you see that this is what happens when
you take a vow? ואחרי נדרים לבקר, Ve-acharei nedarim levaker, after vows,
this is how it's being written, you will be inspected, okay, because
you think you are so righteous that it's not enough, you know,
what the תורה Torah has forbidden that you now are going to
add more prohibitions and so on, so you know, the תורה Torah
is going to check you out and make sure are you really
as righteous as you think you are that you can now, you
know, be adding be adding vows. Now in terms of the formal
question of פתח pesach versus חרטה, charata, right, this is like a
cute way of sort of turning every case into a פתח, pesach,
right? Because it's there's nothing specific about this case that 'had I
thought about X', it's just like in any case, anybody who takes
a vow, if you're, you know, if you were thinking properly about,
you know, about sort of the religious cost of taking a vow,
generic, yes, it's generic, and so we sort of want to do
it through a פתח, pesach, we're not just סתם stam say 'do
you regret', but we want to but the פתח pesach is one
that is sort of very generic. Yes, Michael, what do you want
to say?
At the פשוטו של מקרא peshuto shel mikra is that what, he
checks?
I don't know.
Okay, בוטה, Boteh, yes, pointed this out, but maybe it bears repeating
that, you know, we just had in אבות Avot like, you know,
נדרים סייג לפרישות. nedarim siyag l'prishut.
Right,
okay, so there are different there are different attitudes in חז"ל, Chazal,
and there are also different things that you can bring up if
you want to help somebody get out of his vow, okay? So
meaning maybe even the rabbi himself, you know, maybe more feels that
נדרים nedarim are a good thing but, you know, but wants to
bring up this problem, the problem with it, you know, to help
this guy get out of his vow. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemorah says like this:
ואף על גב דפתח רבי ינאי ליה, Ve-af al gav d'patach Rabbi
Yannai leh, even though רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai opened up with him
this way, אנן לא פתחינן ליה בהא, anan lo patcheina leh b'ha,
we do not use this. Meaning assuming that you cannot you have
to you can't open up with, you know, a well because this
is again just way too, you know, way too generic. Okay,
so ולא פתחינן, velo patcheina, and we also don't open up with
בהא דאחריניתא, b'hadach areinaisa, on the following other one. דאמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן,
D'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan, מאי פתח ליה רבן גמליאל לההוא סבא, mai patach leh
Rabban Gamliel l'hau sabba, what did רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel open up
for a certain elder when he came for, you know, when he
came to get a התרת נדרים? Hataras Nedarim? יש בוטה כמדקרות חרב
ולשון חכמים מרפא, Yesh boteh kemidkorot charev velashon chachamim marpe, there is
there is one who speaks and it's like the piercing of a
sword, ולשון חכמים... velashon chachamim...
and the language of sages heals. So that's just talking about the
harm that certain acts of speech can cause to other
people and how the healing that others can. But this is applied
to נדרים. nedarim. כל הבוטא, ko haboteh, anybody who enunciates a vow,
ראוי לדוקרו בחרב, rauy l'dokro becherev, is worse being is worse being
pierced through by a sword. Okay, אלא לשון חכמים מרפא, ela lashon
chachamim marpei, but the language of the sages can heal because they
can get you out of your vow because they can do a
פתח. petach. All right, so this is interestingly, right, I mean this
is a really central discussion here. At number one it just tells
you the process of think about all the issues that are being
raised right now. Number one is just the halachic issue about the
process of התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim. Number two is the idea that
התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim bases itself on the foundation that when you
take a vow you have to be, you have to be פיו
ולבו שוין, pif v'libo shavin, it's not enough that you said it,
you have to be really have wanted it and therefore we could
explore whether you really deep down wanted it. So that's number two.
Number three is if we're using as a way of getting you
out of it, oh you if you had thought about this you
wouldn't have wanted it, these statements about how bad vows are were
also using this as an opportunity to explore the whole religious phenomenon
of vows, whether is it a good thing or a bad thing.
Now rightly as Michael Shur so said, it doesn't mean that there
are only one sided statements to this. It is true I think
that the weight of this מסכת masekhet as we've discussed before is
trying to rein in the vows that vows had become too prolific
and therefore it's trying to emphasize the problematics of vows, but there
are positive statements as well, but here at least we are highlighting
the negative ones to try to get this guy out of it.
Now why do you not open up with the suggestions? Either one
they're too generic and if you feel that you have to be
פותח poteach with a פתח petach and not just a חרטה charata
you want to really work at the details of the case and
make something about me
specifically why concretely I would not have done it in this particular
case rather than a nice generic, oh yeah, if I had realized
it's a bad thing to take vows I wouldn't have done it.
So number one. Number two, the ר"ן Ran says that these two
things are
very like they make a person very like they could just scare
a person, they're scare tactics. If you had known yeah that the
that you're going to be given the fourth degree up in heaven,
if you had known that you're worth being what is it drawn
and quartered, would you have done it? So it's a scare tactic.
So the guy might say oh no I wouldn't because you just
scared him into saying he wouldn't but but bottom line is he
he maybe doesn't really believe that that's true and he may he
maybe really would have done it anyway but now you've just gotten
him all scared. Okay so therefore we don't open up with this.
All right so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ולא פתחינן
בהדא חניתא v'lo patchinan behada chanayta and we also don't open with
the following sort of suggestion, invitation, דתניא d'tanya we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, רבי נתן אומר, Rebbe Natan omer, הנודר כאילו בנה במה
והמקיימו כאילו מקריב עליו קרבן. hanoder ke'ilu bana bamah v'hamkaymo ke'ilu makriv
alav korban.
That also how bad it is to take a vow, if you
take a vow it's like you build a במה, bamah, like you
build an altar at the time when there's only one altar when
there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash when you're not allowed to build
altars. And if you actually go so far as to fulfill it,
it's even worse. It's one thing to build the altar, but building
the altar you haven't yet offered on it, to fulfill it you're
actually like bringing a קרבן. korban. So this makes the entire act
of a vow and this is such a profound religious statement we'll
read the ר"ן Ran inside in a minute,
it says like look the vows nowadays are sort of I would
say חומרות, chumras, like people feel like I want to do enough
I want to do more than what the religion is demanding of
me. Now the question is okay but the first thing if you
want to do more is you have to identify what is the
primary thing the religion is demanding of you. So people that adopt
חומרות chumras basically feel that the primary thing religion is demanding of
me is like a self restraint,
denial, self restraint and so on, so I want to do more
of that. If somebody felt the primary thing the religion is demanding
of me is learning תורה Torah or doing חסד, chesed, right then
that would then that expression of doing more would take a different
type of an expression. Okay but that's the idea, somebody here wants
to do more. Is that a good phenomenon or not, doing more
as opposed to just doing what God said? Okay, especially if what
the aspect, so that could be just סתם stam as in general,
like nope just do what you're told, we're not looking for any
initiative. Or number two especially if the more is in an area
of self denial. Is this a good thing intrinsically or not? Okay
and that's like building a במה. bamah. Building a במה bamah somebody
wants to do more, they want to bring more קרבנות korbanot and
that's not even about
self denial. But nevertheless your own personal religious experience, maybe religion is
a communal thing, it's a central thing, it's a God imposed thing,
and it's not everybody going off and building a במה bamah for
themselves. Okay, so that's the question here about how you look at
נדרים nedarim and again it's I think a very powerful translation about
questions of religious practice, self-initiated religious practice in general. So let's take
a look here at the ר"ן. Ran. הנודר כאילו בנה במה, hanoder
ke'ilu bana bamah, so the ר"ן Ran says the following. בשעת איסור
הבמות, besha'at issur habamot, when במות bamot are forbidden. ונראה בעיני, v'ne'era
be'einay, דלהכי מדמינן ליה לבונה במה, d'lhachi medaminan leh l'boneh bamah, משום
דסליק אדעתיה דנודר mishum d'salik adaiteh d'noder the one who makes the
vow thinks דמצוה קעביד, d'mitzvah ka'avid, I'm doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Right,
how do I know it's a מצוה? mitzvah? Why does make... things
forbidden on me a מצוה? mitzvah? רחמנא Rachmana אסרה במילי דאיסורא, asra
be-milei de-issura, the תורה Torah makes a lot of things forbidden on
me, so having things forbidden is a good phenomenon, okay? ואי הוא
נמי אסר נפשיה. ve-i hu nami assar nafshei.
So hey, let me do the תורה Torah one better. There you
go. If God is going to make things forbidden, I’ll make more
things forbidden on myself. וקאמר דטעי. ve-kamar de-ta'ei. And what this statement
is saying is that this person erred. Okay. דאדרבה לבונה במה דמי,
de-adaraba le-boneh bama dami, he's more like somebody who builds an altar.
דניהי דרחמנא אסר להקרובי קרבנות בפנים, de-nihi de-Rachmana asrei le-akrovei korbanot bifnim,
it's true God wants you to bring sacrifices in the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, okay, אסר דלא לוסיף עלה עליו לבנות במות ולהקריב חוץ,
asrei de-lo le-hosif ala alav livnot bamot u-lehakriv chutz, the תורה Torah
doesn't want you to do more than that and to build and
to build altars outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. הכא נמי, hacha
nami, here too, דאי דרחמנא אסר עליה דברים האסורים, de-i de-Rachmana asar
alei devarim ha-asurim, the תורה Torah forbid certain things on you, אי
מוסיף איהו אמה דאסר רחמנא, i mosif ihu ama de-asar Rachmana, if
you're adding on what the תורה Torah forbade, פשע, pasha, you sin,
כענין דאמרי בירושלמי בפרק
פותחין לו. ke-inyan de-amrei bi-Yerushalmi be-perek potchin lo. פותחין, Potchin, like the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi says in נדרים, Nedarim, לא דייך במה שאסרה תורה, lo
dayecha be-ma she-asra Torah, what, it's not enough what the תורה Torah
said was forbidden? אלא שאתה אוסר עליך דברים אחרים? ella she-ata oser
alecha devarim acheirim? You have to go ahead and make more things
forbidden? Like okay, the תורה Torah says forbidden, that's enough. You know,
it's not a positive religious phenomenon to have more things forbidden on
yourself.
רמב"ם Rambam quotes this a lot in his discussion about like the,
you know, the golden mean and about striving not going too much
one way too much the other way like, you know, sometimes more
is not better, more is worse. Okay. ושייך בה נמי האי לישנא
משום דנודר מתפיס בקרבן. ve-shayach ba nami hai lishna mishum de-nodeir matpis
be-korban. And he says by the way, it also fits very well
the whole phenomenon of נדרים nedarim because a נדר neder draws on
the קרבן korban phenomenon. Okay. וכיון שאין קרבנו רצוי, ve-keivan she-ein korbano
ratzui, and if your sacrifice is not desired, when you say קונם
konam this bread on me, you're saying this bread is like a
קרבן. korban. But if your קרבן korban is not desired, so then
כבונה במה ומקריב בחוץ, ke-voneh bama u-makriv chutz, it's like you've offered
up a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. You made
a קרבן, korban, but it didn't do, but it wasn't the type
of קרבן korban that God wants. Okay. So therefore, okay, והמקיימו ve-ha-mekaymo
we'll just read the next one, כלומר שאינו נשאל עליו. kelomar she-eino
nish'al alav. And here, if you now, and here you can see
how this really works as a good way to get the guy
a פתח. petach. He says it was one thing, okay, but he
already built a במה. bama. But if you're going to go through
with it, then it's going to be כאילו מקריב קרבן. ke-ilu makriv
korban. And the only way to stop being מקריב makriv a קרבן
korban is to be, is to ask a התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim.
Okay. כאילו הקריב על אותו במה קרבן וחייב משום שחוטי חוץ. ke-ilu
hikriv al oto bama korban ve-chayav mishum shechutei chutz. So we don't
open with this because of course this also is a scare tactic
and is too generic and would just make it too easy and
would also get you people that say they didn't want to do
it because you've scared them into that. But again, a very powerful
statement about the whole attitude towards נדרים nedarim and towards this like,
you know,
self-initiated religious practice. Okay. Of course there are times when במות bamot
were a good thing, when there was no central בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, you know, so you could understand that there are times when
people are feeling, you know, that the religion in its current, you
know, like in its sort of current established form or whatever, you
know, is not answering,
you know, necessary sort of religious needs that they have and that
there's an importance to do these types of things, you know. So
anyway, but it is interesting in terms of that general discussion about
sort of the self-initiated,
make it do it yourself religious experience, and also very much particularly
in the context of making things forbidden, you know, based on the
sort of way the ר"ן Ran and the before him the רמב"ם
Rambam have read this issue, which is the making things forbidden itself
might not be an intrinsic good type of a religious expression. Yes.
Do you look at the last line and a half before the
דיבור המתחיל dibbur hamatchil in the ר"ן Ran הנודר כאילו בנה במה?
ha-nodeir ke-ilu bana bama? Yeah. He says ויש לחוש שיאמר שמתחרט אף
על פי שאין מתחרט.
ve-yesh lachush she-omer she-mitcharet af al
pi she-ein mitcharet. Right,
that's the scare tactic.
So is the ר"ן Ran just being imprecise by saying it's a
matter of חרטה charata rather but the סוגיא sugia is about פתח?
petach?
Oh, yeah. I mean, it's true.
I think that even a פתח, petach, no, I understand that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It's a good point.
Yeah, he's just being generic.
He's like, you know, yeah,
I think he's being generic because I think at the end even
a פתח petach means I wish I hadn't done it. מעין חרטה.
me-ein charata. Yeah, speaking loosely. Yeah.
It's kind of coming over
and saying,
you know, I want to get out of it. Essentially he's saying
that had I thought that I wouldn't have, so it's essentially a
type of saying I regret, but it's not just again going straight
to the I regret. Yeah, that's true. There is an, basically it
all does fall under the broader rubric of חרטה. charata. Okay. So
now back to the גמרא. Gemara. ברישא פותחינן. be-reisha potchinan.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this. ברישא פותחינן. be-reisha potchinan.
Now, in the beginning of this, maybe we do open up, meaning
maybe we do say you it was כאילו בנה במה. ke-ilu bana
bama. That would not be so so heavy that because you haven't
yet been brought the קרבן korban on the במה, bama, there's no
real איסור issur you violate by building a במה, bama, it's only
by offering on it. So maybe we will say to a person
it won't be so heavy. such a scare tactic to say, you
realize by having made a נדר, neder, it was like you built
a במה. bama. That we would do. But בסיפא, besayfa, the end
of the statement, כאילו מקריב קרבן, ke'ilu makriv korban, that if you
go through with it, you're going to be like bringing a קרבן
korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, אביי אמר פתחינן Abaye amar
patchinan where we will open up with this. So אביי Abaye actually
says we're okay to open up with the whole statement and we're
not afraid it's a scare tactic. רבא אמר לא פתחינן, Rava amar
lo patchinan, we don't open up with it. רב כהנא מתני לא
להשמעתא בהדין לישנא, Rav Kahana masni lo lehashemata behadin lishana, רב כהנא
Rav Kahana says a different version of this. No,
his version was what we just did. רב טביומי מתני הכי, Rav
Tavyumi masni hachi, here is how רב טביומי Rav Tavyumi teaches it.
בסיפא לא פתחינן, besayfa lo patchinan, we don't open up with the
end. Everybody can agree that we don't say it's like you have
brought a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That's too
much of a scare tactic.
ורישא, ureisha, how about opening up with the beginning? It's like you
built a במה bama and would you have done it had you
realized it was like you built a במה? bama? אביי אמר פתחינן
רבא אמר לא פתחינן. Abaye amar patchinan Rava amar lo patchinan. That's
the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava whether we open with
that or not. והלכתא, vehilchasa, and the הלכה halakha is לא פתחינן
לא ברישא ולא בסיפא. lo patchinan lo bereisha velo besayfa. We don't
open with the beginning or with the end.
We don't say, we don't even say it's like you built a
במה, bama, let alone saying it's like you were מקריב makriv a
קרבן. korban. So basically the upshot of all of this is we
don't open up with any of these scare tactics. Now I want
to say something. Does this mean, what if we would say all
of these were a type of a פתח? pesach? Let's say we
would say that you could actually open up with חרטה. charata. Just
say, do you regret ever having made it? So if I could
say that, that's pretty generic. Am I also allowed to say had
you realized that you would have been deserving of being drawn and
quartered, would you have made it? So the answer might be no,
you're not allowed to say that. Even if you're allowed to just
open with חרטה, charata, which is generic, and do you regret it?
At least asking me if I regret it is not a scare
tactic, right? It might be generic. It might be telling me it
might be true that like you're not saying something specific concretely, you're
just sort of saying in hindsight I wish I hadn't done it.
But at least you're not forcing me or scaring me to say
something I don't really think. Okay. So therefore this idea that you
don't open with these scary things is not just might not just
be saying that this isn't a good פתח. pesach. It might be
saying that even if you could open with חרטה, charata, you don't
open with these statements. These statements are just scare tactics and they'll
get you an answer that's not a really honest answer. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara continues. ולא פתחינן בהא נמי דשמואל. velo patchinan
beha nami deShmuel.
We also don't open with the statement of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל
אף על פי שמקיימו נקרא רשע, deamar Shmuel af al pi shemekaymo
nikra rasha,
even a person who fulfills his vow is called a רשע. rasha.
Okay, similar to previous statements. אמר רבי אבהו מאי קרא, amar Rabbi
Abbahu mai kra, where is what verse do you see this based
on? דכתיב וכי תחדל לנדור לא יהיה בך חטא, dechativ vechi techdal
lindor lo yihyeh becha cheit, if you stop vowing there will not,
you won't have sin. ויליף חדלה חדלה, veyalif chadala chadala, and you
make a גזירה שוה gezeira shava from to stop to withhold from
another פסוק pasuk of חדלה. chadala. כתיב הכא וכי תחדל לנדור, ketiv
hacha vechi techdal lindor, when you cease to vow. וכתיב התם שם
רשעים חדלו רוגז. uchetiv hatam sham reshaim chadlu rogez.
The name of the wicked
have or שם sham I think it might be שם רשעים חדלו
רוגז. sham reshaim chadlu rogez. There the wicked have ceased their creating
of
anger and discord. So anyway, so you see that the word חדלה
chadala is associated with the word רשע. rasha. All right, so we
don't say that either, another scare tactic. אמר רב יוסף אף אנן
נמי תנינא, amar Rav Yosef af anan nami tenina, we also taught
the idea that somebody makes a vow is called a רשע. rasha.
כנדרי כשרים לא אמר כלום, kenidrei kesherim lo amar klum, if you
say this should be forbidden to me like the vows of כשר
kasher people you didn't say anything because כשר kasher people don't make
vows. כנדרי רשעים, kenidrei reshaim, but like the vows of wicked people,
everybody probably remembers this משנה Mishna it was so bizarre, נדר בנזיר
בקרבן ובשבועה. nedar benazir bekorban uveshvuah.
That would be a good vow whether it was a נדר, neder,
נזיר, nazir, or קרבן korban or שבועה. shevuah. Okay. אמר רב שמואל
בר נחמני. amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani. So now we are done
with well we're going to for we're pausing in this discussion of
whether you are how you open up with somebody, give them a
פתח pesach which is a scare tactic. The upshot is you don't
give a פתח pesach which is a scare tactic. Okay, and it
was as I said an opportunity to talk about how the phenomenon
of making vows at least with a whole range of statements saying
why it's a very bad phenomenon. That's not necessarily the only idea
in the גמרא Gemara but it's certainly something you could use to
get a guy to say he wish he hadn't done it, okay,
and I would say it's the dominant idea of the גמרא Gemara
in נדרים Nedarim that these vows are not a thing to be
embraced. And now we're going to pause and have a little digression
in some unrelated אגדתא agadata and then turn back and get back
to this question about פתח pesach and חרטה. charata. Yes.
But even if the פתח pesach is not a scare tactic, shouldn't
we still open with חרטה? charata?
No, no, no. No, if it's not a scare tactic, פתח pesach
is always better because פתח pesach is specific and concrete. It's like
had you been thinking about the following what your neighbors would have
said, had you been thinking about this would you have done? He
said oh no then I wouldn't then it's a very sort of
specific and concrete reason why we can identify why you didn't really
mean it as opposed to חרטה charata which is just too generic,
too non-specific. Did you regret it? Yeah, I regret it. So therefore
so the whole point is that there's a question whether you open
in חרטה. charata. Everybody agrees you can open with a פתח. pesach.
Okay, but this is at this פתח pesach is a generic scare
tactic פתח. pesach. That's the difference. Okay, so now the גמרא... Gemara...
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, since we mentioned anger, there the wicked have ceased their
discord, their anger.
So, אמר רב יונתן Amar Rav Yonasan or יוחנן, Yochanan, כל הכועס
כל מיני גיהנום שולטים בו. kol hakoes kol minei gehenom sholtim bo.
Anybody who gets angry, all forms of גיהנום gehenom take, take you
know, take over this person. שנאמר, Shene'emar, והסר כעס מלבך, vehaseir kaas
milibecha,
remove anger from your heart, והעבר רעה מבשרך, veha'aveir ra'ah mibsarecha, and
then you will remove evil from your flesh. ואין רעה אלא גיהנום,
ve'ein ra'ah ela gehenom, רע ra is גיהנום. gehenom. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כל
פעל ה' למענהו, kol poal Hashem lema'anehu,
everything that God has done is for God's sake, וגם רשע ליום
רעה, vegam rasha leyom ra'ah, the
same for the evil person to the day of evil. So the
idea that there's a day of evil means not just generic evil
but some sort of punishment, very concrete specific punishment that's awaiting a
person, okay, and therefore it's גיהנום. gehenom. Now of course, the question
is do you understand what anger is? Well, I don't think so,
I think it's just a digression. Could be though, Michael could be
right, that since part of the פתח petach or whatever, part of
the whole discussion, the ר"ן Ran certainly has been bringing up is
that people would do it in a fit of anger, although the
גמרא Gemara doesn't, right, that's a good point, the גמרא Gemara doesn't
tie that in but it very much could be right that that's
another reason it's brought in, but I think it's also specifically because
anger was mentioned. The other thing I will say is do you
understand גיהנום gehenom here in חז"ל Chazal in the meaning of this
line literally, like you know, they really were talking about a punishment
a person would get in the world to come, or do you
understand it you know figuratively, like if you know, if a person
gets angry then all different, you know it's sort of like you
know fire, like they get steamy and then that affects themselves and
then it affects you know their actions and all different types of
bad things will come to you, right, as a result of your
anger, which is a right, which then sort of basically is just
getting back to the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk in, where
was the פסוק? pasuk? In no, in קהלת, Kohelet, הסר כעס מלבך
והעבר רעה מבשרך. haseir kaas milibecha veha'aseir ra mibsarecha. It's just a
more you know metaphorical graphic way of talking about that. Like all
of, all of the forces of גיהנום gehenom will come down on
you, you know, because of how that will impact you and your
actions and your state of being. Okay, yes.
I didn't mean it
as a punishment at all, I didn't mean it as a punishment,
I meant it as a natural outcome of being angry. Exactly, your
out of control, it eats away at you, you know, you become
irrational, it eats, you know, it eats at your, you know, your
insides burn up, right, you know, it's so I think but that's
really just פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk in קהלת. Kohelet. The
גמרא Gemara has just made it more graphic, okay, so, okay. ולא
עוד אלא שהתחתוניות שולטות בו. Velo od ela shehatachtoniyot sholtot bo. He
also gets hemorrhoids. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ונתן ה' לך שם לב רגז,
venatan Hashem lecha
sham
lev ragaz, there we get the angry heart, okay, וכליון עיניים, vechilyon
einayim, a blindness of the eyes, ודאבון נפש, vedaavon nafesh, a languishing
of the soul. איזהו דבר שמכלה עיניים ומדיב את הנפש, Eizehu davar
shemechaleh einayim umadiv et hanafesh,
what is it that like hurts the eyes and is bad for
the soul, the spirit? הוי אומר אלו התחתוניות, Hevei omer elu hatachtoniyot,
that's hemorrhoids. So I'm not exactly sure how to read hemorrhoids metaphorically
here, but okay. Anyway, yeah.
It's just a tremendous, it's amazing how much they knew that we
learn today. In other words, there is a way that you can
react emotionally that can affect your internal functions.
Right, absolutely, absolutely, your whole system
is a reflex of anger and שם כעס. shem kaas.
Aha,
so
yeah your eyes affect yeah, how it affects your eyes, yeah definitely,
and your soul. Meaning the idea right that it affects your eyes
and your soul, that's in the פסוק pasuk and that's you're right
you know certainly right how you look at things, how you feel
or whatever. What it has to do with identifying it concretely with
hemorrhoids unless again it's just a way for people to have a
you know to concretize you know that feeling of what that would
mean, yeah.
I think it's related to the word שחור. sechor.
Oh, that's interesting. Oh, that's a nice point. Directly related. Oh, that's
interesting. Like you pucker up. Yeah. And you're binding your.
Oh okay very nice. Okay let's move on. Shhh, עולא. Ulla. No,
Shhh, עולא, Ulla, דמסיק לארעא דישראל, d'maseik le'ara de'yisrael, when עולא Ulla
went up to Israel, אתלוו ליה תרי בני חוזאי, itlavu leh trei
benei chuzai, two people from חוזא Chuza accompanied him בהדיה bahadei with
him. קם, Kam, now
while they were going, קם חד שחטיה לחבריה, kam chad shachteh lechaverei,
one of they got into a fight and one of them killed
the other one. Okay, God, they got very angry, here's an example
of anger taking you over and it was murderous, it led to
killing the other one. אמר ליה לעולא, Amar leh le'ulla, so the
murderer said to עולא, Ulla, יאות עבדי? ya'u avdi?
Did I do well? Did I you know did I kill him
well or something or is it okay what I did? אמר ליה
אין, Amar leh in, yes, ופרע ליה בית השחיטה. uparelai beit hashechita.
Now there are two versions of this. One is עולא Ulla himself
like sort of stretched out the guy's the neck of the murder
victim, or it says לך פרע ליה בית השחיטה, lech parahlai beit
hashechita, go and expose or whatever you know the neck of the
murder victim meaning like open up the wound to make sure that
he dies quick. Or עולא Ulla himself did that. Now it's going
to be clear he did that because he was afraid for his
own life. So if a murderer says to you holding the bloody
knife, was it good that I killed this guy? Okay, you say
yes. So then the גמרא Gemara says, כי אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן,
ki ata lekamei de'rabbi yochanan, when he came to Rabbi יוחנן, Yochanan,
אמר ליה דילמא חס ושלום אחזיקי. amar leh dilma chas veshalom achzeiki.
Maybe
God forbid I reinforced the hands of somebody who was you know
who did this terrible sin? I told him he did the right
thing. So אמר ליה amar lei he said to him נפשך הצלת.
nafshecha hatzalta.
No you saved yourself I mean obviously normally you should never say
something like that but sometimes you know self-protection comes first. Okay קא
תמה ka tamah Rabbi Yochanan now when Rabbi Yochanan heard this story
he was astounded. מיתיבי metivei כתיב ksiv ונתן השם לך שם v'nasan
Hashem l'cha sham
God will give you there in exile לב רגז lev ragaz
so an angry heart. So here somebody got so angry to murder
somebody else. בבבל כתיב b'vavel ksiv
that the idea of that you're going to have that anger that's
talking about in exile in בבל. Bavel. How did this happen when
you came to ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? אמר ליה amar lei ההוא
שעתא hahu sha'ata no at that moment לא עברינן ירדנא lo avrinan
Yardena
we had not yet crossed over the Jordan we were still in
חוץ לארץ chutz l'aretz and that's how we could have that anger.
Okay which is pretty funny if you consider the fact that like
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you had all of these sects warring
against each other you know very sort of passionate there was a
lot of enmity and a lot of anger going on in Israel
much more than we have a sense took place in בבל. Bavel.
But anyway yes.
Right but you know we're kind of glossing over this but does
this not perhaps raise the issue are you allowed to hasten someone's
death if they're already dying
you know like these end of life issues? Well that would be
a good question that's an excellent point like whether Ulla himself was
פרע ליה בית השחיטה para lei beis hashchita or he said לך
פרע ליה בית השחיטה. lech para lei beis hashchita. You know it's
a good question whether if you're like like you say you know
you're right that is a very good question if like if there's
something which is יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor somebody's afraid for
their life and somebody else is already dying the idea of חיי
שעה. chayei sha'ah. It's a question of חיי שעה chayei sha'ah and
how חיי שעה chayei sha'ah plays the function in הלכה. halacha. So
it comes up in other areas like the חיוב הצלה chiyuv hatzala
for somebody with חיי שעה. chayei sha'ah. Somebody who actually you know
is terminal and can they take a certain procedure you know which
will extend their life I don't know like a you know a
few months do they have to do that or not? Actually they
don't have to do that. I mean I'm talking very broadly here
go ask your local פוסק. posek. Okay but but because you know
the חיוב הצלה chiyuv hatzala for חיי שעה chayei sha'ah is different
than for on the other hand somebody who kills somebody you know
that he you know that but but anyway the point is is
that's an interesting question. Like would finishing would somebody in the process
of dying and hastening it be יהרג ואל יעבור? yehareg v'al ya'avor?
Right that's essentially what you're asking. Because he was afraid for his
life he was afraid for his life.
Or is there a reason or or maybe he did it because
the guy was in agony?
Right and then he was doing and then it was like a
euthanasia it was a euthanasia type I mean of thing right which
is yeah so you're right it's a very good I mean in
discussions of medical ethics I yeah I don't remember I mean it's
a very good point you know this could could be relevant at
least as a way of thinking concretely about some cases. Yes I
appreciate that. Thank you. Okay let's go on in the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רבה בר בר חנה Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Chana כל הכועס
kol hakoes back to being angry anybody who gets angry אפילו שכינה
אינה חשובה כנגדו. afilu Shechina eina chashuva k'negdo. He doesn't even care
about God right? Which is true you know people get so angry
nothing matters. They'll say things that they wish they would have never
said right well there you go they'll say נדרים nedarim but they'll
say things to their spouses or to their friends or to loved
ones right that they wish they could that they can never take
back you know and they'll you know the mistake it might even
be that person will be will transgress something you know that שבת
Shabbos and they don't care they're so angry they're jumping in their
car they're driving the heck out of here you know things don't
matter anymore when you're angry you don't think straight. Okay שנאמר shene'emar
רשע כגובה אפו בל ידרוש אין אלהים כל מזמותיו rasha k'govah apo
bal yidrosh ein Elokim kol mzimotav the wicked person when his anger
gets you
know rises will not seek
out God is not in any of his thoughts. רב ירמיה מדפתי
Rav Yirmiyah midifti אמר amar משכח תלמודו ומוסיף טפשות. meshakei'ach talmudo umosif
tipshus. It's funny this seems like a little anti-climactic after everything we've
just said. It'll cause you to forget your your learning and you
will become stupider okay makes you do dumb things and forget things
you should know better about but here it also seems like it'll
have a lasting impact on your knowledge. שנאמר shene'emar כי כעס בחיק
כסילים ינוח ki cha'as b'cheik k'silim yanu'ach because anger will reside in
the heart of in the in the bosom of the foolish. וכתיב
uchsiv וכסיל יפרוש אולת uchsil yifros ivalas and a the the um
the foolish person will spread out his foolishness you know his um
okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak אמר amar בידוע
שעונותיו מרובים מזכויותיו. b'yadu'a she'avonosav merubim mizchuyosav. If somebody gets angry you
know that it's a not now not talking about the effects of
the anger but what it what it indicates. It points to the
fact that this person has sinned more than they have done meritorious
things. שנאמר shene'emar ובעל חמה רב פשע uva'al cheima rav pasha and
the person with who has anger is a person who has abundant
sin. Okay. אמר רב
אדא בריה דרב חנינא Amar Rav Ada brei d'Rav Chanina אלמלא חטאו
ישראל ilmalei chatu Yisrael had Israel not sinned there's a question of
אלמלא לו ilmalei lo or אלמלא ilmalei a whole question of whether
the word אלמלא ilmalei means had they done this or had they
not done this but okay anyway here it means
had Israel not sinned um in the חטא המרגלים cheit hamiraglim very
relevant just this last week's פרשה parsha לא ניתן להם אלא חמשה
חומשי תורה וספר יהושע בלבד. lo nitan lahem ela chamisha chumshei Torah
v'sefer Yehoshua bilvad. All they would have needed we would not have
had all of תנ"ך Tanach we just would have had the five
books of Moses and יהושע. Yehoshua. Why would we have had יהושע?
Yehoshua? שערכה של ארץ ישראל היא she'ercha shel Eretz Yisrael hi Yehoshua
talks about the value of the land of Israel, about the dividing
and about what was in each, what was in the the different
sections of the different tribes, anyway you still need יהושע Yehoshua to
get a little closure on the story that they actually made it
into the land of Israel,
but anyway, but you wouldn't have needed any of the rest because
the whole purpose of all the rest of the נביאים, Nevi'im, at
least talking about the, you know, the, what do you call it,
נביאים אחרונים, Nevi'im Acharonim, thank you, the נביאים אחרונים Nevi'im Acharonim is
all to give מוסר, mussar, you know, to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
for their sins. Of course, it's some of the most beautiful and
poetic and articulating the vision of values of the תורה Torah that
we have, but its initial purpose was to basically give מוסר. mussar.
I don't know why we wouldn't have needed the נביאים ראשונים, Nevi'im
Rishonim, I guess it's another indication that the גמרא Gemara is saying
that, you know, Jews aren't so interested in history, but of course
still, I mean נביאים ראשונים Nevi'im Rishonim is just history? It's not
just also about like, you know, teaching us religious lessons? But again,
maybe had we not sinned we would have learned all the religious
lessons we would have needed from the five books of משה. Moshe.
One minute, okay, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Okay, כי ברוב חכמה רוב
כעס, ki berov chochma rov ka'as, cause the the increase of the
wisdom of these books of wisdom, the books of תנ"ך Tanakh was
a result of the increase of anger. Because we had, you know,
we had, we had become anger, we had got anger, I don't
mean anger at השם, Hashem, but in this context it's our anger
led us to sin, although it is interesting like attributing all of
the sin that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael had done to anger. So
maybe again it does mean God's anger. Anyway, all of this, you
know, the sin is what led us to have all these books
of the נביאים, Nevi'im, which are books of חכמה, chochma, so it's
good that we have them because we learned a lot of wisdom
from it, but ultimately it was all a result of sin. Yes,
Bobby.
I just wonder, when we hear about this anger as such a
negative force, what does it mean when we read that God has
anger?
Well okay, but that's a general, I mean, the word God has
love and God whatever, I mean, oh, you mean oh, I see
what you're saying, you're saying like
so that's a good question, you know, I mean,
I'll give you a very short answer, meaning, you know, like the
גמרא, Gemara, there's a גמרא Gemara for example that says like קנאה
kina is very bad thing, right, jealousy or whatever, you know, so,
and says how could jealousy be such a bad thing if it
says like God is אל קנא? El Kana? So גמרא Gemara says
okay, you know, there are times when it's appropriate, you know, used
in the very controlled and right measure and right time is when
it's appropriate, but it's about sort of, you know, but that's maybe
in very small measures and very, you know, specifically chosen times as
opposed to when it spills out. So that's like one type of
an answer. And the other thing that I will say is that,
you know, that רמב"ם Rambam deals with this question: if we're supposed
to imitate God, which aspects of God are we supposed to imitate?
You know, you know, like if you say, well, you know, look
at all the things God does, God brings life to the world
and healing to the world, well somebody else could say, what do
you mean, God brings hurricanes and destruction and disease and illness, maybe
I'll imitate that? Or well let's look at how the תורה Torah
describes God, you know, the תורה Torah says, you know, God loves
and God cares, well the תורה Torah also says God gets angry
and God kills, so which are the parts that I'm supposed to
imitate? So רמב"ם Rambam says that's why, actually talking about the נביאים,
Nevi'im, the way you know how you're supposed to imitate is the
ways in which the נביאים, Nevi'im, not you know sort of used
to describe the names they use to describe God. They say, you
are God, אל רחום וחנון ארך אפים ורב חסד, El rachum vechanun
erech apayim verav chesed, right? So but it does also say God
is an אל קנא, El Kana, okay, but, but anyway, but the
רמב"ם Rambam says that those are the words that identify like what
are that aspects that we're supposed to emulate. But you raise a
profound theological question, it really is a good one. Okay.
Look, anyway, sometimes, you know, it's important, there's another גמרא Gemara that
says like that you sometimes have to make your kids look like
you're angry when you're not in order so that they, you know,
learn a message, right? So, alright. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Let's get back to נדרים. Nedarim.
Okay, אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, אין נזקקים לאלוהי ישראל. ein
nizkakim lelohei Yisrael. If somebody uses the name, says in the name
of, in the name of the God of Israel, you do not
respond to them and try to, you know, as taking a vow,
I mean as getting them out of their vow. חוץ, chutz, with
the exception of, קונם אשתי נהנית לי, Konam ishti nehenis li, קונם
Konam that my wife cannot, you know, should not get any benefit
from
me, שגנבת כיסי ושהיכתה בני, sheganvas kisi veshehiksa banai, because she stole
my wallet or she hit my
kids, okay, ונודע שלא גנבה ושלא היכתה, venoda shelo ganva veshelo hikta,
and then it turns out that she didn't do that. Now this
is very bizarre. First of all, if he says this is why
I'm taking this vow, because I think my wife did this, and
it turns out she didn't do it, then that's, you don't even
need התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. That's a case of נדרי שגגות, nidrei
shegagos, which we haven't gotten to yet, but it basically means taken
on false premises, and therefore you really didn't mean it, and you
don't even need התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. So so there's some discussion
that the ר"ן Ran has about that, and some therefore take out
even that line. line of שהקיצה בני shehiktsa banai and he didn't
do it. Like even if he did do it, we're talking about,
even
if she did do it, excuse me. But before we even get
to that, I just want to say what this means for אלוקי
ישראל. Elokei Yisrael. So there's two interpretations of this. The ר"ן Ran
means, and this gets back to the point that Dov made before
with all of these technical terminologies, sometimes the גמרא Gemara can be
very imprecise. And the word נודר noder could really mean to take
a שבועה. shvua. And the ר"ן Ran and תוספות Tosfot and
רמב"ם Rambam think the word that think when it says that somebody
says אלוקי ישראל, Elokei Yisrael, it means that that's how you take
an oath in the name of God, dot dot dot. So we're
actually talking about a שבועה. shvua. And the point is we've talked
about doing התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim. What about doing a התרה hatara
for a שבועה? shvua? And this issue comes up later, the debate
of בית הלל ובית שמאי. Beit Hillel u'Beit Shamai. בית שמאי Beit
Shamai says you never do a התרה hatara for a שבועה; shvua;
that's much weightier, okay? And that's like taking God's name and it's
an oath, it's sort of like about your honesty and integrity, it's
not about a status that you're then changing of a status. Okay,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel says you do do התרה hatara for
a שבועה. shvua. So this is saying that even maybe according to
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, if you take a שבועה shvua with the
name of אלוקי ישראל Elokei Yisrael and God's name, we're not going
to do it, we're not going to do a התרה hatara with
the one exception of a case of שלום בית. shalom bayis. Your
שבועה shvua is getting between you and your wife. Okay, and it
says and we've seen this is a phenomenon that happens, a person
could take a נדר neder or שבועה shvua or whatever to not
have sex or other types of things, and then we will remove
it. And the ר"ן Ran says very—or רש"י Rashi says very beautifully—he
says, like the גמרא Gemara says that God says by סוטה, Sotah,
my name that was written בקדושה bikdusha should be erased in order
to make שלום shalom between husband and wife, so even when my
name is taken in a שבועה, shvua, the שבועה shvua should be
undone in order to make peace between husband and wife. A very
beautiful parallel between that מדרש. midrash. Okay, so that's understanding this as
a שבועה. shvua. The problem is is that it says קונם אשתי
נהנית לי, Konam ishti nehenet li, which is totally לשון נדר. lashon
neder. So there is then approach of רש"י Rashi as opposed to
ר"ן Ran and תוספות Tosfot that say actually we're talking about a
נדר. neder. And even a נדר neder is weightier when you use
God's name. Now that's an interesting idea, because we have never seen
this idea that a נדר neder matters about using God's name. It's
all about making a status in the קרבן. korban. But if somebody
said, "This thing is a קונם konam to me in the name
of the God of Israel," okay, that's a weird hybrid right between
a נדר neder and a שבועה. shvua. You're still talking about the
status of the object, but you're saying it in God's name. So
that's so that type of a hybrid רש"י Rashi says, that's what
we're talking about. We're not talking about a שבועה, shvua, talking about
a נדר, neder, but a נדר neder using God's name. And that
type of a thing we're going to be reluctant to undo unless
there's a real issue of שלום בית. shalom bayis. Now the other
question has is there also an aspect of טעות ta'ut here? Does
it also require that it was done on false premises and so
on, that you thought your wife hit your kid and then it
turns out that she didn't, but some switch gears here because if
that is really what happened, then it just never was binding in
the first place. Okay, but then now let's just see a little
bit more about this. Okay, ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דרב אסי, Hahu de'asai
lekamei d'Rav Assi, if somebody came in front of רב אסי. Rav
Assi. אמר לה, Amar lah, ההיא, Hahi, excuse me. ההיא דאתאי לקמיה
דרב אסי. Hahi de'asai lekamei d'Rav Assi.
אמר לה, Amar lah,
he said to her, במה נדרת? B'mai nadart? What did you take
a vow? באלוקי ישראל? B'Elokei Yisrael?
So, in the name of the God of Israel? אמר לה, Amar
lah, he said to her, אי נדרת במוהי, i nadart b'mohi, had
you just taken a vow with במוהי, b'mohi, which is either a
language of שבועה shvua or it's a language of if you
remember משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, but it was some type of a
כינוי, kinuy, some type of a euphemism for a שבועה. shvua. So
even if you had just said that,
שהיא כינוי בעלמא, shehi kinuy b'alma, had you just said that, שהיא
כינוי בעלמא shehi kinuy b'alma which is just a כינוי, kinuy, מזדקקנא
לך, mizdakkekna lach, then I would have attended to you. I would
have gotten you out of it. If it was a normal שבועה,
shvua, we'll read it the ר"ן's Ran's light that we're talking about
שבועה. shvua. השתא דלא נדרת במוהי אלא באלוקי ישראל, Hashta d'lo nadart
b'mohi ela b'Elokei Yisrael,
now that you didn't do it, again notice the word נדרת. nadart.
That's why this is so confusing. Now that you didn't do it
in the word במוהי b'mohi but in the name of the God
of Israel, לא מזדקקנא לך, lo mizdakkekna lach, I will not attend
to you, I'm sorry, I can't help you. Okay, but again this
confusion, are we talking about a שבועה shvua or about a נדר?
neder? רב כהנא איקלע לבי רב יוסף. Rav Kahana ikla l'vei Rav
Yosef. רב כהנא Rav Kahana came to the house of רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. אמר ליה ליטעום מר מידי. Amar lei lita'om mar midi.
Now
you're going to see that even the sages used נדרים nedarim and
שבועות shvuot in the most trivial of cases. He said to him,
okay, רב יוסף Rav Yosef said to him, "Have a little bit
to eat." אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said, "לא, lo, no, מרי
כולה, mari kula, the master of all, in the name of God,
right, ריבונו של עולם. Ribbono shel Olam. לא טעימנא, lo ta'imna, I
won't have anything to eat." Now that's a clear לשון שבועה, lashon
shvua, so that makes it clear that at least here we're talking
about a שבועה. shvua. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so the host said back to him, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said back to him, "לא מרי כולה לא טעימנא ליה. lo mari
kula lo ta'imna lei.
No, in the name of God, I won't feed you anything! You
say you won't eat anything, I say I won't feed you. I'm—you're
not fired, I quit! Or, okay, or you can't quit, you're fired!"
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, "הא ניחא לרב כהנא." ha
nicha l'Rav Kahana. So this is good according to רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, דאמר, d'amar, "לא מרי..." lo mari... אלא רב יוסף ela Rav
Yosef or רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמאי אמר לא מראי כולה? amai
amar lo ma'arei kulei? דאמר הני ניחא לרב כהנא de'amar hani nicha
lerav kahana we understand what רב כהנא Rav Kahana said he said
דאמר לא מראי כולי de'amar lo ma'arei kulei no in the name
of the master of everything I won't eat. אלא רב יוסף ela
Rav Yosef or רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמאי אמר לא מראי כולה?
amai amar lo ma'arei kulei? Why did he say that? Why do
you have to now take, you take a שבועה shvua you're not
going to feed him? He already take a שבועה shvua that he's
not going to eat. So הכי הוא דקאמר ליה hachi hu dekamar
lei no here's what he was saying to him: לא מראי כולי
הוא דקאמרת. lo ma'arei kulei hu dekamart. One minute. You said no
in the name of the master of the, of God, you won't
do it. So הלכך hilkach is that if because since you took
it in the name of אלוהי ישראל Elohei Yisrael even though you
didn't use like שם השם shem Hashem in Hebrew you just referred
to God like the master of all, but since you brought God
into the equation therefore לא אטעמתיה לך lo ateimteih lach I can't
give you anything to eat. I can't get you out of your
נדר neder or out of your שבועה. shvua. So you took a
שבועה shvua in the name of God I can't get you out
of it.
So did
he
say that in the name of God I won't feed? Well that's
how we're rereading it is that he did not say back to
him the same thing he just said I can't help you. Okay
let's just read let's wrap up here one more line and then
we're going to end a little early. אמר רב אמר רב נחמן
הלכתא Amar Rav amar Rav Nachman hilchata I know but I want
to end a little early. הלכתא פותחין בחרטה hilchata potchin becharata because
this is the bottom line. Bottom line is we asked are you
פותח בחרטה? poteach becharata? Yes you can open up for somebody and
say do you regret without anything concrete. Do you regret? Yes I
regret. Fine we're done. Okay. ונזקקין לאלוהי ישראל venizkakim l'Elohei Yisrael
and not only that even if somebody says אלוהי ישראל Elohei Yisrael
we are so we have a much more liberal approach than the
more restrictive ones that we had thought right? We are much more
willing to help people get out of their vow. We don't want
to keep people burdened by their נדרים nedarim or their שבועות shvuot
even if they bring God into it we will go ahead and
release them from that.
Now we'll stop there for now but I want to read there's
a case coming after this but I want to just look at
a ר"ן Ran here very important. Look at the ר"ן Ran the
first wide line he says the following: He says אמר רב נחמן
הלכתא פותחין בחרטה ונזקקין לאלוהי ישראל. Amar Rav Nachman hilchata potchin becharata
venizkakim l'Elohei Yisrael. פירוש פותחין בחרטה בין בנדר בין בשבועה. peirush potchin
becharata bein bineder bein bishvua. ונזקקין נמי לכתחילה לאלוהי ישראל. venizkakim nami
l'chatchila l'Elohei Yisrael. ולא שנא velo shena first he says נקט חפצא
בידיה nakat heftza beyadei או לא נקט חפצא בידיה. o lo nakat
heftza beyadei.
Even if somebody is holding onto a ספר תורה Sefer Torah when
they take a שבועה shvua we'll get them out of it. ואפילו
כי נקט חפצא נזקקין. va'afilu ki nakat heftza nizkakim. דלא חמיר חפצא.
delo chamir heftza. חפצא heftza means a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. אלא
ענין שבועת הדיינים. ela inyan shvuat hadayanim.
It's only done when the court makes you take an oath ליומויי
עלה leyumuyei ala to make you afraid to put the fear of
God into you or meaning like this is the idea of putting
your hand on the Bible. That doesn't really add anything to the
weight of a שבועה shvua but psychologically it does. And if we
get you out of your שבועה shvua we'll get you out of
your שבועה shvua if you took it in God's name and with
your hand on the Bible we can still get you out of
it. אבל עיקר שבועה בשם או בכינוי הוא. aval ikar shvua be'shem
o be'chinuy hu.
Okay now period. So basically we will get you we'll always be
prepared to get you out of it. Now we find a fascinating
pushback of the גאונים. Geonim. ואף על גב דאמר גאון ve'af al
gav de'amar Gaon the גאון Gaon
says whoever the גאון Gaon is מאן דאשתבע בספר תורה בעשרת הדברות
אין לו הפרה עולמית. man de'ishtaba be'Sefer Torah be'aseret hadibrot ein lo
hafara olamit.
We would never undo a vow in the name of if it
was in the name of the Ten Commandments or with a hand
on the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. ליתא למילתא כלל. leita lemilta klal.
Okay we don't that's completely wrong. הדין הוא דינא דגמרא hadin hu
dina degemara דאפילו שבועה נזקקין ופותחין בחרטה ואין צריך לומר לנדר. de'afilu
shvua nizkakim upotchin becharata ve'ein tzarich lomar leneder. אבל רבינו האי aval
Rabbeinu Hai
now
five lines down in the wide lines רבינו האי ז"ל Rabbeinu Hai
zal החמיר בנדרים hechmir binedarim was strict שלא לפתוח בחרטה shelo liftach
becharata that you do not open against the גמרא Gemara you don't
open with a חרטה. charata. ואמר דאנן השתא אי עבדינן כרב אשי
עבדינן ve'amar de'anan hashta ei avdinan kerav Ashi avdinan we'll only do
something like רב אשי Rav Ashi דאמר אין חכם מתיר אלא כעין
ארבעה נדרים. de'amar ein chacham matir ela ke'ein arba'ah nedarim. It has
to be like a פתח petach we won't really open with a
חרטה. charata. כלומר בפתח אבל בחרטה לא. klomar be'petach aval becharata lo.
So number one we need a פתח. petach. Number two going against
exactly against everything we just concluded. והחמיר עוד ve'hechmir od and he
was also strict and he said בשבועות ואמר דלא מזדקקינן בהו כלל
bishvuot ve'amar delo mizdakkinan behu klal
and by a שבועה shvua even with a פתח petach we won't
get you out of a שבועה shvua because that's weightier. אלא היכא
דאיתרמי מילתא דאית ביה תקנתא או מצוה ela heicha de'itrami milta d'it
bei takanta o mitzvah כגון עשיית שלום בין איש לאשתו kegon asiyat
shalom bein ish l'ishto unless it's for something like שלום בית shalom
bayit a שבועה shvua we'll never get you out of. So the
גמרא Gemara says we'll get you out of everything. He says נדר
neder only with a פתח petach and שבועה shvua never at all
unless it's a שלום בית. shalom bayit. Then he
says אבל הרב הנשיא אלברגלוני aval Harav Hanasi Elbargeloni
this is five lines from the bottom okay ז"ל כתב. zal katav.
So that's the opinion of רב האי גאון Rav Hai Gaon basically
much more מחמיר machmir than the גמרא. Gemara. ובשם מר יהודאי גאון
u've'shem Mar Yehudai Gaon in the name of מר יהודאי גאון Mar
Yehudai Gaon here different opinion. שהחמיר
עוד she'hechmir od I'm sorry this is even more strict בנדרים binedarim
והושוו לשבועות. v'hushvu l'shvuot. So while רב האי Rav Hai אמר דלא
מזדקקינן אפילו בפתח amar de'lo mizdakkinan afilu be'petach the same way we
won't get you out of a שבועה shvua we'll never get you
out of a נדר neder even with a פתח petach unless it's
for something like a מצוה mitzvah and שלום בית shalom bayit אלא
דבר מצוה ela devar mitzvah שמתירין אותם בפתח ולא בחרטה she'mattirin otam
be'petach velo becharata וכל שכן דוקא פתח דחכם החמירו. v'chol sheken davka
petach d'chacham hechmiru. אבל פתח דבעל לא החמירו. aval petach de'ba'al lo
hechmiru. פתח דבעל petach de'ba'al that's
only by התרה hatara not by הפרה. hafara. And then by the
ר"ן Ran end and then the ר"ן Ran end. So basically he
says according to the גמרא Gemara you can get anybody out of
anything even a שבועה בשם השם shvua be'shem Hashem holding onto a
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. That's the הלכה. halacha. But the גאונים Geonim
established more as a as a as a policy, maybe to make
it more weighty to people. There's always a tradeoff. You make it
more weighty, but then you get people much more stuck and they
have to deal with the consequences, right? So this raises an important
question, which might have been going through our גמרא Gemara the whole
time. How easy or how hard you make it for people, like
the more you want to help them after the fact, the more
you're making a slippery slope beforehand, right? So maybe you strike a
balance. The גמרא Gemara came out totally to make it easy at
the end, and the גאונים Geonim gave a total pushback and said
שבועה shvuah never, נדר neder maybe only with a פתח. petach. And
then רב יהודאי גאון Rav Yehudai Gaon said even a נדר neder
never, unless there's a real overriding concern. You should be interested to
know that both רמב"ם Rambam and שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פסקן pasken
the גמרא, Gemara, not the גאונים. Geonim. And they basically say that,
well, sometimes the גאונים Geonim change the course of things, at least
as a policy issue, if not מעיקר הדין. me'ikar hadin. Anyway, the
רמב"ם Rambam and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פסקן pasken the גמרא
Gemara that we will always get somebody out of a שבועה shvuah
and of a נדר, neder, you know, and it's important again, the
idea of even אלוהי ישראל Elohei Yisrael and the power of שלום
בית, shalom bayit, but the real conclusion is that we'll always find
a way, you know, we'll always be available to get somebody out
of that.